for
all right welcome everyone how is
everybody feeling doing great awesome so
one more reminder to please fill out the
first day survey before Friday because
what we're going to do Friday is try to
coales together into teams and you know
start meeting each other Etc so the
better you know your classmates and the
better they know you the better so if
you could fill it out by hopefully
Wednesday or Thursday at the latest uh
then it'll give us enough time to
organize everyone coess and then start
creating teams for the mentoring session
on Friday so on Friday is one of the
formal mentoring sessions so in addition
to the first day survey we're going to
ask you to sort of complete um one page
profile and we're going to give you more
information about that but basically for
now um just remember to um upload your
profile all right all right so uh here
we are uh with uh lecture two expression
analysis so here's where we are so we
are now entering the first module on
genomics epig genomics single cell
networks and
circuitry today we're going to start
with expression analysis which is going
to be fairly oh sorry
I don't know how to hide the
[Music]
captions you guys see caption
somewhere okay I think if I hit alt they
should go
away okay anyway I apologize for oh no
this is actually a feature it's for
those who cannot hear me there's always
a text we're trying to be inclusive here
um okay so I apologize it's hiding part
of the text uh screen um okay so the
goal of module one is to basically uh
first today we're going to look at
expression analysis and we're going to
introduce the concept of clustering and
classification more broadly in the
context of supervised and unsupervised
learning and we're going to sort of
include some ideas of semi-supervised
learning and so on so forth we're going
to first introduce a very simple
algorithm known as K means and then
we're going to see how this is in fact
about gaussian mixture models and we're
going to sort of you know get into the
mood for machine learning and Bas on
inference and generation versus
discrimination
Etc on Thursday we're going to talk
about sequential data and an alignment
dynamic programming here Mark of models
you know parsing um posterior decoding
hmm
architectures next week we're going to
get into Gene regulation so we're going
to talk about Regulatory genomics and
epig genomics uh um how do we understand
the motives of Gene regulation how do we
model the signal of hiso modifications
Etc then we're going to have a formal
lecture on all of the intricacies of
single cell genomics today we're going
to see a very simple version of that
that focuses on the pure machine
learning clustering classification
components but then there's a lot more
complexity and that we're going to cover
in a dedicated lecture that talks about
both single cell genomics but also
spatial transcriptomics and Next
Generation techn ologies and also
nonlinear embeddings that we're going to
be visualizing today but really diving
into the methods of uh in a few weeks
and lastly we're going to talk about
graphs uh principal component analysis
dimensional reduction uh you know
regulatory circuitry and so on so forth
so that's the goal for module one H
which we're starting today for module
two uh we're going to be looking at
protein structure module three chemistry
module 4 ehrs Etc sounds good excited
about module one so again these course
is called uh machine learning in
computition biology so today is going to
be our for first formal introduction to
um machine learning so you know first
what is machine learning machine
learning is the ability to
improve on a task with more training
data okay a lot of people have been
talking about AI since the 60s they're
like oh artificial
intelligence artificial intelligence is
not necessarily machine learning
artificial intelligence could be oh I'm
going to code in a bunch of cases and
decisions that the machine is going to
make so that it looks
intelligent but if that machine is not
getting better with more data it's not
actually machine learning is everybody
with me here so that's the that's the
key idea first there's a task then it's
about training
data and it's improving sounds good
awesome so
um what is that task that task could be
many many different things the two tasks
that we're going to be talking about
today is classification and also
clustering classification is a form of
supervised learning that's when we know
the answer when you know the
answer
then there's somebody supervising the
algorithm when you don't know the answer
it's unsupervised learning so basically
one task could be how well can I
classify Alzheimer's patients from
controls
with more data if I'm getting better
that's a type of learning everybody with
me here another task could be regression
I want to predict the uh age at which a
person will get Alzheimer's regression
is when I'm predicting a number not a
class everybody with me
here transcription could be simply
taking a voice stream and doing what you
see on the screen here that I couldn't
get rid of translation could be doing it
in you know buch of other languages like
Greek French Spanish you name it um this
could be structured output namely I
could speak and it could be you know for
example I could be speaking to a patient
about their diagnosis and the Machine
could be creating structured data from
this so when we talk about structure
versus unstructured data unstructured
data is usually free text or an image
structured data is you know two mer size
seven the image is just a bunch of
pixels it's unstructured tumor size 7
it's something that you have inferred
from the image everybody with me here
diabetes stage
severe that's structured
data unstructured data is well you're
starting to show symptoms of cognitive
decline you know we're a little concern
Etc okay that's unstructured data free
text everybody with me here now machine
learning used to be very much about
structured data basically you have a
bunch of variables and you're doing
stuff with those variables it's about
data it's about numbers
I'll show you some slides where that
dichotomy between structure and
unstructured data is starting to get
lost where you can basically start doing
clustering as we're going to see today
but now on documents on text on you know
patient records or patient
responses okay so it could also be
anomaly detection for example you have a
bunch of streams and at some point you
want to raise the alarm like oh the
patient has fallen down so basically
Dina katabi up you know upstairs she's
basically modifying Wi-Fi to be able to
sort of observe people walking in their
homes and there's going to be all kinds
of activities at some point you're going
to have to make a detection to say okay
call the cops call the medical you know
team so that's anomal detection
synthesis is about taking a lot of data
sets and then you know summarizing them
better sort of inferring something about
the field imputation means finding
missing data and then filling it in and
then Den noising means um finding
sources of variation that are not
necessarily meaningful that are
non-biological that are simply uh you
know perhaps Technical and so so forth
everybody with me here so in all of
these tasks through the course we're
going to see techniques that allow you
to get better with more data and that's
going to be you know what we call
machine learning and then when we say
improve on a task that basically means
we need to have some kind of performance
measure that tells us that indeed we are
improving everybody on board
good
questions okay so now when we talk about
training data this is what what we're
going to call the experience okay and
then the experience is either the Rober
running around in the in the world or
the AI agent monitoring you know
interaction with patients on or figuring
out how the doctor is responding to
different circumstances getting better
at this okay so that's basically our
working definition of machine learning
okay good now we're always talking about
making inferences about the world and in
competition biology there there's always
going to be something that is observed
and those those are going to be the
expression values for example for a gene
and then there's something that's going
to be hidden and that's you know the
patient has
Alzheimer's and we're going to
distinguish these two different worlds
there's the world of the measurements
and then there's the world of the
model and inferences is inferring
something about the hidden state of a
system based on observations about that
system okay so what are the observations
for example if you're looking outside I
don't know some long hole in a wall and
you can see that like there's a lot of
bright light you might infer that it's
you know summertime when you woke up for
example or if you see you know lot of
gray you might infer that there's you
know rain or sorry that it's fall based
on the observation of rain so basically
when you see snow outside it's
unmistakable it's snow it's rain it's
cloudy it's Sun this is the
observations the inferences is you know
what season it is or what is the you
know storm system that is going on above
me and I have isolated observations but
from those observations I'm inferring
something about hidden state of the
world why do we care about that because
I can then make additional predictions I
can basically say oh perhaps I shouldn't
go sailing because there's a storm
building up okay so that's the whole
point that
you're observing parts of the world and
then you're inferring something about
that world about about you know yeah
something about the underlying
hidden drivers of those observations so
this is the world of observations of
data of of you know measurements and
this is the world of models of
hypothesis of inferences everybody with
me here so far right so very often it's
going to be easy to express the forward
probability of an event that basically
says when it's winter then there's you
know I don't know 60% chance of snow
when it's summer there's I don't know
60% chance of sun okay so these are the
forward probabilities
and this is typically the way that we
express systems why because they're easy
to measure you're basically saying okay
now it's summer I can measure a bunch of
stuff and then this is what I find or I
have an Alzheimer's patient I can
measure their expression patterns this
is the probability of having that Gene
Express highly when you have
Alzheimer's inferences are going to be
about reversing that directionality of
the arrow it's basically saying given
that I observe rain what is the chance
that there's a storm system above me
okay given that I observe High
expression of I don't know some
lipoprotein Gene what is the probability
of Alzheimer's okay so very often we're
going to be talking about the forward
probabilities and that's the generative
probability in other words I am in a
state of the world for example I'm in
the summer State and I'm sampling
observations from that
state based
on knowledge that it summer and a series
of observations I can infer the
probabilities of that generative model
generating samples from a distribution
so for example I'm
sampling temperature readings from I
don't know June and then I get a
distribution of temperature readings now
now given that I have a
given reading I can say where does that
reading fall in that
distribution and from the reading and
the underlying model that I have of say
the standard deviation and the mean I
can say okay well the June State
generated 72 degrees with you know this
probability the July State generated 72
degrees with a different probability and
now I can start making inferences about
is it more likely to be June or July
based on the measurement that I have is
everybody with me I mean this is a
terrible example because this is Boston
so it doesn't actually work that way
Boston basically just shuffles all the
day just randomly pulls out of weather
and then so so you know imagine we're in
some other sort of well behaved climate
zone okay everybody with me here awesome
so so basically when we talk about a
generative model we're basically talking
about the sampling probabilities from an
underlying model that is able to
generate observations of the world okay
and therefore we have the probability of
an observation given the season or the
probability of snow given winter or in
general probability of you know a
measurement given a state of the world
and what we're trying to do is reverse
the arrows and basically make an
inference about what is the probability
that the patient has Alzheimer's give
even a bunch of gen Express
measurements okay so basically uh we
have the probability of the data given
the
hypothesis or the state of the world if
you wish and then we're trying to infer
the probability of the state of the
world I.E patient Alzheimer's from the
observations i e I measured you know
this expression for that Gene in that
tissue okay and that's where Bas rule
comes in so basically when we talk about
basian inference it sounds fancy but
it's just simply we're using base rule
to reverse this Arrow we have the arrow
of probability of hypothesis given data
and then we're flipping it around by
talking about the probability of data
given hypothesis hypothesis given data
is like given data hypothesis so the r
is pointing down data given hypothesis
is um sorry that's the arrow pointing
down data given hypothesis so we have
hypothesis we generate data so that's
the arrow pointing you know given
hypothesis data and then this is given
data hypothesis in other words you know
we're trying to infer the up pointing
aror okay and this is super simple it's
basically simply the probability of a
hypothesis given the data is the data
given hypothesis times the probability
of hypothesis over all the data divided
by the probability of the data over all
the hypothesis okay to explain that
super super simply it's um you know the
purple area is simply the fraction of
the world that's red times the fraction
of the red ones that are also blue but
the purple area is also the fraction of
the world that's blue times the fraction
of the blue that's also red in other
words P of a given btimes P of B in
other words P of B is the fraction
that's blue and then P of a given B is
the subset of that that's red P of B
given a given P of a is like simply P of
a that's red and then this is the part
of red that's also blue purple everybody
with me here so that simple to derive
and then you know from that you get P of
a given b equals this divided by B and
that divided by a okay and that in the
context of basian inference is simply
that the posterior probability what does
that mean why posterior because I've
seen the data so post means after so
after seeing the data then the prob of
my hypothesis is something okay so
having seen snow my probability of
winter is something everybody with me
and then having seen the expression of
you know a gene my probability of
Alzheimer's is something and from and I
can infer that from Simply what is the
probity of expression of that Gene given
Alzheimer's but notice I have to worry
about the prior for Alzheimer's
basically very very often you know
people confuse those two and they're
like oh yeah well if this is higher of
course this is higher and yes it's true
but for hypothesis that have vastly
different priors
then this is absolutely not true okay in
other words I you know I take a test for
some rare
disease the test comes back positive
what's more likely that I have the
disease or that I don't have the disease
it's still more likely that I don't have
the disease and the reason is that the
probability of having a rare disease is
like I don't know what in a
million a given rare disease having some
rare disease is much higher because
there's tons of rare diseases but having
a given rare disease that probability is
extremely high that's why we don't go
around testing people for everything the
doctors just don't go you know testing
for everything because these tests are
fallible they basically wait to to have
some hypothesis that you might actually
have the disease based on some symptoms
and then they do the test for that
disease everybody with me here so
basically that prior is extremely
important when you start thinking
about you know rare events for example
having Alzheimer's or you know the test
might come back
positive but the prior might be so so
small okay so that's why we need to
worry in basan inference very much about
not just the likelihood that's the
probability of collecting the data when
the hypothesis is true in other words
you know seeing something given that I
have Alzheimer's but also the prior
which to the probability that the
hypothesis is true before connecting the
data we call it prior because it's
before the data posterior after the data
okay now this bottom here is the
marginal this is simply the probability
of collecting data under all possible
hypothesis so what's P ofd P ofd is p
ofd given H1 * P of H1 plus P ofd given
H2 * P of H2 plus P of D given H3 * P of
H3 Etc so this is the integral over all
possible
hypothesis does that change the most
likely hypothesis the most likely model
basically for example if I'm worried
between Alzheimer schizophrenia or
bipolar for a patient does that change
anything no it doesn't the only thing
that matters is the prior when I'm
comparing between different hypotheses
because that marginal is going to be the
same for all of them okay the total
likelihood the the total probability is
going to be the same for everybody with
me here awesome any
questions
okay so in that context of basically you
know basian inference we're going to be
first introducing very simple algorithm
for clustering and then we're going to
basically see that it's just a
simplification of a much more General
algorithm for gaussian mixture models
what are gaussian mixture models is
basically when you have a mixture of
multiple gaussians generating data so
I'm sampling data from the green
distribution I'm sampling data from the
red distribution I'm sampling data from
the blue
distribution and then I observe a bunch
of data points
that's the actual process generating the
data but I don't know that process in
advance what I need to do is figure out
what is the number of
clusters where are the centroids of
these clusters what are the spreads and
distributions for each of these clusters
Etc okay so unsupervised learning is
going to be about without any guidance
as towards green red or blue inferring
what is the underlying distribution that
might be generating my data and that
distribution might sometimes be a
mixture of Gauss everybody with me here
awesome so this is unsupervised learning
and then supervised learning basically
says oh I've sampled a bunch of green
points I sample a bunch of red points I
know the labels for those points I get a
new Point what is
it okay so if I get a gray Point
somewhere around here you're going to
guess red if you get a gray Point
somewhere around there you're going to
guess green if I get a gray Point
be like well you know it's hard to tell
everybody with me
here so basically these are the two main
tasks that we're going to be talking
about clustering and classification so
basically clustering is here
classification is here and in a toy
example we're going to be you know
thinking about uh expression for example
in the brain or expression in the liver
and the you know single dimensionality
projection of this is going to give you
some perhaps separable data but
projecting on for example liver there
might be some overlap but if you look at
both dimensions together the data become
more separable everybody with me here
awesome so we're going to be talking
about a set of objects that are
characterized by one more features the
features are going to be all of the
measurements we have and when we talk
about 20,000 dimensional objects it's
simply that we did 20,000 measurements
for example all of the genes in the
human genome it's routine to just
measure all 20,000 gen and then you have
20,000 features now how well can I
classify every person in the room using
20,000
features super
well you know I can figure out exactly
who's wearing a blue shirt or a pink
shirt or a you know I don't know green
earrings or you name it why because I
have 20,000 features super easy right so
basically we're going to be wearing a
lot about do I have too many features do
I have way more features than objects if
you know if I have I don't know 70
students and 20,000 features super
trivial you know I I can certainly find
a gene that classifies any one person in
the room okay yeah have so many features
visualiz
ITA very very good point so I'm going to
be showing you plots that are usually
two-dimensional because you know we're
human and we're having trouble
visualizing more than two certainly more
than three dimensions so most of the
time I'm going to be showing you some
lower dimensional projection of these
very high dimensional data and I'm going
to show you some of those and when we
get to the corresponding chapter
lectures probably lecture seven we're
going to be talking a lot more about how
those are made now pca's principal
component analysis basically says what
are the major components of variation if
you look at here the major component of
variation is this one and the next one
is that
one now I went and measured expression
of let's say this Gene in brain and that
Gene in liver is that the right
dimensionality or is the right
dimensionality some underlying process
for example lipid metabolism over
expression in that person that then gets
reflected both in the expression in the
brain and in the expression of in the
liver so maybe that principal component
maybe that combination of
features is actually where the true
biology
lies and then what I'm seeing is
different projections which are only
capturing partial information about the
true underlying biology is everybody
with me here
so sometimes these axis of variation are
going to be interpretable and it's going
to be oh simply the combination of those
two features other times the global axis
of variation will be completely
meaningless because we've taken 20,000
Dimensions we compress them down to
two but then the local variation will
still be very meaningful at least
biologically for example as you're
moving in One Direction you might see
that oh those cells are more Alzheimer's
and those cells are more more healthy
that Dimension absolutely means
something but it is reflected in perhaps
3,000 measurements at the same time
because all of these genes are slowly
increasing their expression along with
Alzheimer's but the true biological
variable is Alzheimer's does that make
sense so basically we're going to be
talking about both linear and nonlinear
dimensionality reduction and the linear
one is when I when I do
PCA and the nonlinear is for example t
and umap and other sort of you know
projections
yeah so if you do learning method like
clustering and you see really strong
clusters can you turn that into like a
classifier or can you start adding your
own labels to these things validation so
so if I see this data and I say oh well
that's class one that's class two that's
class three and then I say okay how well
can I classify those three classes I'm
going to be doing really great because I
Define the classes based on my
clustering and if I say oh this point
was labeled Alzheimer's but it's
probably a mistake let me relabel it
control I'm going to do a little data
clean up my classification is amazing so
you have to be very cautious about that
in the sense that uh statistically if
you basically first look at the data
there's whole things of the whole slew
of things that you can no longer do
because you've you know dirtied your
mind by looking at the data you suddenly
are soiled because you can't think
unbiased anymore so that's going to be
one challenge however you could say well
I'm going to do PCA and then you know
find the principal components of the
data that's an unbiased operation you
don't need to like it won't change based
on what you see but the M say and I
found 10% components best explained that
the difference between Alzheimer's and
non-alzheimer's that's biased If instead
you say I find that 10 components
explain the most relative variation you
know and then there's diminishing
returns after that and therefore I'm
going to stop after 10 components before
looking at the Alzheimer's
classification then you're good so
basically you have to constantly be
thinking how much did I bias the
analysis because I peaked at the result
beforehand so however there's a whole
class of semi-supervised learning where
you basically have some points that are
labeled some points that are not labeled
and therefore instead of having all
points that are green or red here and
then a gray Point shows up you have a
ton of gray points and maybe you know
three red labels and two green labels ET
so that basically means that you have to
somehow use the structure of the data to
understand the overall patterns of
variation and then after that you can
kind of layer in the classification
component and now you can kind of use
both the structure and that there's also
uh self-supervised learning what is
self-supervised learning self- certifed
learning is a lot what we see with AI
right now I talked about in the first
lecture where we basically have you know
billions of
images and no time to annotate them all
so I'm going to hide a patch of the
image and I'm GNA ask hey what's hiding
in this patch I'm going to turn the
image black and white and say hey what
was the color I have the answer because
it came with color but now the machine
doesn't have the answer because I only
gave it the BL the black and white so
for the machine to figure out how to
color it it better understand what our
world looks like and therefore build
underlying models of the world but now I
have as much labeled data as I want for
free because I just remove the color and
I'm asking for the color again this is
known as a pretext task I don't care
about that task I have the color I hit
it so I don't care for the answer you
know you don't have to be get really
good at it but getting really good at it
means that in doing so you're learning
about the state of the world so
semi-supervised learning and
self-supervised learning kind of blur
the boundaries between supervised and
unsupervised these are fantastic
questions any other questions
okay great so classification you have
labels and you want some kind of rule
that will accurately assign labels to
new points existing points so easy new
points is where you know the rubber hits
the road and the sub problem very often
is feature selection namely maybe
there's a bunch of extraneous features
maybe those two are perfectly correlated
with each other maybe I don't need both
maybe the true biology is here maybe I
have to sort of construct
you know
some
inferred features from the measurements
that I have those infert features could
be some kind of linear or nonlinear
combination of those features for
example this plus that or this times
that or this Square divided by that Cube
or you name it okay so this is you know
sort of feature
augmentation and that allows you to
sometimes find
Dimensions through these combinations of
your existing measurements where the
data becomes linearly
separable and that's what support Vector
machines are all about it's like that's
what the kernel construction stuff comes
in it's basically a fancy form of not
feature selection but feature inference
feature construction okay and when I
talked about representation
learning in the first lecture or I
should say call call it lecture zero
basically in the intro lecture I talked
about representation learning
representation learning is really about
feature inference so you have a bunch of
pixels but you're inferring meaningful
features and those meaningful features
are closer to the underlying biology to
the causality to the mechanisms than the
raw measurements okay so very often
we're going to Care to infer the true
dimensionality of the data the true axis
of variation and maybe instead of having
brain expression liver expression of X
or YZ Gene maybe the act of variation
would be male female
Alzheimer's control young old you know
African-American you know european-
American and so so forth is everybody
with me here so these might be the True
Dimensions of variation of your
data and if you can understand enough of
the structure of the data to understand
these latent dimensions of
variation
unsupervised and then ask hey what did
they mean and then you're like oh well
this correlated with age or with sex Etc
then you're doing really
great there's an alternative which is
you can start with age and then say okay
what correlates with h let me now take
that component out okay what's
correlating with sex biological sex let
me take that component out what's
correlating with you know disease St let
me take that component out you can
progressively peel components of
variation and then you can do an
unsupervised clustering of the rest or
you name it everybody with me
here cool other question
okay um so again classification has some
labels there's some kind of feature
selection and the metric you can
actually have a metric because you know
what's green and what's red you can hide
the label of this point present it to
the model as gray and say how well did I
reconstruct it what is my false positive
was my false negative rate
Etc clustering has no
labels and it's very hard to sort of
have a metric for how well are you
clustering so the goal is to group
points into some clusters based on how
near or proximal they are to each other
and to identify some kind of structure
in my data and the metric is usually I'm
going to bring in some
other measurement that I haven't shown
to the algorithm and I'm going to ask it
how well are you capturing that
measurement of course if that
measurement is highly correlated with
one of the measurements that I already
have that's a problem basically usually
I want to have some kind of independent
validation that's not just like maybe um
yeah it could be for example an Imaging
data set or it could be a performance in
a different test or something that was
not used in the deciding of what's
Alzheimer's okay awesome so again I'm
you know this is the first lecture
technically so so I I I I I think it's
important to sort of distinguish all of
these different types of things so so
basically we've talked about AI we've
talked about machine learning we've
talked about deep learning and I can't
know try to introduce them at the
beginning so basically Ai and comass is
many many things including systems that
pretend to be smart where everything's
hardcoded for example a knowledge based
or a rule-based you know robot that's
still artificial intelligence okay
within that is machine learning and
that's basically what I'm getting better
at uh at a task with more data okay so
for example AI could be simply you know
I have some input I have some hand
design program that de decides what to
do based on that input and then I have
an output the learning part are the gray
boxes here okay with classical machine
learning you basically have design by
hand some features these are the
measurements that you're making and then
you're inferring the parameters with
which you weigh these features and
that's the learning part the more data
you have the better that waiting will be
everybody with me
here conversely if I uh not not
conversely further uh within machine
learning there's representation learning
and that's basically when I don't design
the features by hand to start with I
don't say oh expression of this Gene in
brain is you know a good feature for
Alzheimer's instead I say ah go figure
out the
features okay and then from the go
figure out the features it could
basically do some kind of principal
component analysis or it could do all
kinds of other things to infer what are
good features to even use in inferring
the output and I can learn the features
just based on the input I could
basically say great what are components
of
variation or I could learn the features
that give me a better classification for
the
output okay so I could basically say oh
let me infer some features map the
weight of those features and then infer
the output and now back propagate how to
improve the
features and then try again update the
weights I get a slightly better
classification I go back and I update
the features again okay so the concept
of learning not just the weights but the
features themselves that's what
representation learning is about is
everybody with me here yeah um what
would that look like for something like
expression
R would would it be hand designed
features if you give it like the actual
expr values or in a representation model
what would you have to give it instead
yeah that that's exactly right so
basically the vanila sort of
representation learning approach would
be okay let me now infer like some
linear combination of features or some
nonlinear combination of features and
then I can see every pair of features
that could be a
representation the difference with deep
learning is that these features are not
built at just one level
they're
built on each other so basically I'm
learning some simple features from these
features I then learned more complex
features from the more complex features
I then learned even more complex
features basically having multiple
layers of combinations of gene
expression values is you know where this
would be okay and that's why we call it
deep because you're learning multiple
layers of more and more abstract
features
everybody with me here awesome basically
that's sort of the hierarchy that we're
going to see and then within deep
learning there's generative AI Etc so
basically there's uh you know more
classes that are being
constructed who feels that they've
learned stuff yes awesome all right
let's Dive Right In so with classical AI
the way that machines were kind of
learning how to play chess was that the
human would program all of the rules of
Chess it would hand you know the human
would handcraft a scoring function for
every position and you know the machine
would then search the moves that it can
make for the white to maximize the score
then for the black to minimize the score
then for the white to maximize the score
again for the black to minimize the
score and that's sort of a Minimax
algorithm that basically says at every
step I will choose the thing that
maximizes my score and my opponent will
choose the thing that minimizes my score
and I will choose the thing that
maximizes my score and so on so forth
okay and this is
Gary Kasparov so I met him in Croatia
he's a really awesome guy our kids the
same age and we also play chess I will
not tell you who on this is an exercise
the um so so basically the machine
basically infers from the rules that the
human made and perhaps from some scoring
function that the human made I don't
know how many of you guys made a you
know chess game in your youth but you
know there was a time that we would
basically say oh what is this the best
scoring function for where the Knight is
and you know based on the night being in
the middle you know it has more
controlling squares and therefore it has
a higher value and I can use that to
score every position and humans would
basically come up with awesome scoring
functions and then the machines would
basically just run through these really
really fast run the Minimax algorithm
and then that's where Kasparov lost to a
machine back in 99 or something like
that and then the the world was shaken
you know at the time we thought that
humans would be unbeatable at this kind
of thing and eventually you know
machines got better and better and
better you know anyway I'm not going to
get into what's happening now but you
know needless to say a lot A lot has
changed so this was the classical way
that humans would play chess and then
based on this we had this concept of you
know things that are easy for humans and
things that are easy for machines okay
or hard for machines and the things that
were hard for humans were things like
chess or you know math integration or
remembering like I don't know 3,000
things or reasoning and you know
planning and logic Etc but those it
turns out were kind of easy for machines
you could basically start you know
planning out a path by just simply you
know doing depth research or breath
resarch and then sort of trying every
possibility you could you know play
chess by simply testing every possible
option and then there was this dichotomy
of things that were basically very easy
for humans that you know we didn't think
of as
intelligent and then you know the
intelligent part was things like playing
chess okay but it turns out that the the
the classical AI stuff was basically I'm
I'm sorry to be so provocative but
things that humans had to get trained
at in other words math integration
nobody's born knowing how to do
integration you know we we kind of go
through school to figure out how to do
this nobody's born knowing how to be a
good doctor oh you learn how to follow
flowcharts and that what makes you an
awesome doctor you basically look at
that evidence oh you forgot that one
you're not as good of a doctor okay and
guess what that's not what humans are
best at that's what machines are best at
so we trained humans to be machine like
in a bunch of tasks and those were the
hard tasks at the time because it took
us many years of education to learn how
to do something properly but machines
super easy that's what they do best
where deep learning is going and where
the modern movement of generative AI is
going is kind of that the opposite the
stuff that humans are kind of born
knowing how to do like you know you're
born knowing how to drive a car well
maybe not but anyway you're born how to
recognize to learn how to recognize
images babies can recognize IM is even
before their retina is like fully
functional and their visual cortex is
fully formed like you can recognize
patterns just you know from just being a
baby it doesn't take any special skills
can recognize people that's that's what
we do best and that turned out to be
super super hard for the
machine but it's kind of embarrassing
because the machines are now getting
super super good at these things and
maybe general intelligence lies
somewhere in that direction my guess is
that it lies somewhere in both
directions basically right now the
movement is very very much towards you
know sort of large language models that
you know have enough parameters to
understand the world but I think there
might be some room for learning the laws
of physics and you know having some kind
of equation and some kind of structured
modeling of knowledge and knowledge
graphs and stuff like that maybe but
again we'll find out we don't know where
AGI is my guess is that it's already
here and you know we're just not called
for that because we're protecting our
own I don't know
vanity or confidence anyway so so but
again if AGI is already here then we
don't have to worry about it hasn't
killed us all right so so you know
there's a good way of seeing everybody
with me here awesome so uh again sorry
for taking the time to sort of explain
these Concepts but they're going to be
hopefully helpful for thinking and
conceptualizing about this so when we
talk about deep learning we basically
mean that there's layers of
abstraction building on features on
features on features and that's
basically what's being done inside our
deep learning apparatus that we call our
brain okay so basically we have layers
in our cortex and then individual
neurons are sort of sensing perhaps
pixels and then they're sending signals
and now you can arrange neurons in a
pattern that will recognize you know low
activation High activation low
activation you can hardcode that in your
brain and then when you see an edge the
neuron that recognize that pattern will
fire and that's one layer of abstraction
and now that you have an edge recognizer
you can kind of build you know a
recognizer of uh triangles and so on so
forth based on those features so
basically the concept that you can learn
from the building blocks more and more
abstract items is what you know is at
the foundation of deep learning we'll
talk a lot more about that when we get
to image analysis and we've basically
expanded this Hardware uh like our
actual cognitive Hardware dramatically
since you know Divergence from the chimp
a few few million years ago so basically
humans have expanded this neocortex
which was already insanely enlarged you
know from mammals to primate and um you
know has just gotten wild and again if
you look at most humans you kind of
think of the eyes as the top of the face
but if you've taken a drawing class you
realize that the eyes are actually the
middle of your face and we just have
some hair here but when you see an
extraordinarly smart human without hair
you kind of realize that the eyes are
kind of in the middle okay but all all
of you have the same thing just you have
hair um all right so so basically that
architecture was basically utilized in
the visual cortex but guess what we
studyed the motor cortex nearly
identical architecture you studi the you
know all of these sensory cortices are
nearly identical in architecture receive
signal abstract it abstract abstract it
and then you know boom you get something
out of that and then the Last Frontier
is the prefrontal cortex basically where
all of your cognition and thinking
happens and guess what that's the same
architecture so basically this concept
of abstractions and reasoning you know
might be inherent to sort of how humans
think can function and this is what I
was describing in you know the the
introductory lecture when I was talking
about this representation learning okay
maybe all of these layers are just
really good at abstraction at sort of
learning more and
more
complex
inferences about the world so we have
the world of data we have the label the
Y the prediction and then this is where
the magic happens this is where the
latent uh spaces are okay so
again what we just saw will apply
everywhere okay so yes we are in the
expression analysis lecture but it's
also the intro to machine learning intro
to sort of all of these you know wealth
of both techniques but also ways of
thinking about the world everybody with
me here awesome all right so now let's
basically see how we can use machine
learning for gene expression analysis
how can we learn how can we get better
at a task with more data first we're
going to look at um you know gene
expression analysis in general then
we're going to look at this gausian
mixture model of you know uh
I think it's a very nice Foundation to
start thinking about machine learning
and inference and then we're going to
sort of look at actually an easier
version of K cluing but let me uh Dive
Right so first of all what is gene
expression analysis you basically start
with a tissue you then infer where for
example the nuclei are and that's
usually much easier to capture in a
tissue as complex as brain you extract
nuclei you package up nuclei in
individual bubbles that have the same
barcode for all of the cells in that
bubble and therefore all of the RNA
molecules inside that one cell in that
one bubble have the exact same barcode
you then
sequence all of the reads that come out
and what you get with what would get
back is barcodes for individual cells
that I'm going to now call the green
cell of course there's no caller it's
just barcode GD dtdc ABC or something or
AGC definitely not b um and from that
you will say oh all of these reads came
from the same cell is everybody with me
here and therefore in the end you're
going to have all of the measurements
that you saw an RNA molecule from Gene 2
in the same cell I'm just going to
number them arbitrarily cell one cell
two cell three and you're going to get
an expression Matrix which is simply the
number of times I saw an RNA molecule
mapping to that region of the genome
that corresponds to each gene with a
barcode corresponding to cell
one okay it used to be that it was
expensive to sequence and every letter
that you read from the DNA cost $1 and
to sequence the three billion letters of
our DNA it took three
billion right now it takes about
$300 so we're talking about seven orders
of magnitude from a billion to 100 okay
just and therefore instead of just
hybridizing a read to a region with a
probe we just re sequence whatever it's
re sequence okay and that's basically
how we do
quantitative expression analysis we're
basically just simply
tagging with DNA bar codes
individual cells and then
measuring and you get back a matrix
everybody with me
here and then you basically have a
number of uh like you have 20,000 human
genes maybe I don't know four million
cells and you get a matrix like that and
from that you can do your principal
component analysis Etc and you can find
clusters and classification ET everybody
with me here so basically you dissociate
single cells you do sequencing based
counting of RNA read for every Gene then
you have the counts for every cell you
have multiple samples and cells from
every different condition so you might
have a bunch of Alzheimer's patients and
all of these reads you're going to call
as Alzheimer's
reads and you can think of this as a
flat model that simply says oh I get
like that many cells from Alzheimer's
patients or as a hierarchical model
first I sample a patient then I sample
cells from that patient and so so forth
so that's sort of the hierarchical
approach of of seeing it and then you
can basically do clustering or
classification everybody with me here
awesome so very simply we're going to be
measuring 20,000 genes in hundreds of
conditions in thousands of cells and
we're going to be ending up with every
condition where I did a measurement I
get the expression of a bunch of genes
sometimes partitioned by cell and then
for the next condition the next
condition the next condition this could
be I don't know 400
individuals and that basically gives me
an expression profile for a given Gene
across these conditions so I can start
asking questions about the experiment
Dimension or about the gene
Dimension everybody with me
here so we can ask how similar are two
genes in their expression patterns and
how similar are two experiments in their
expression patterns everybody can here
awesome so now what's clustering
classification clustering is basically
saying okay I have these genes by
conditions
Matrix and I'm just going to find common
patterns I'm going to find genes that
behave similarly across conditions and
conditions that behave similarly across
genes everybody can hear this is just
about finding common structure the goal
of cluster is to group similar items
that likely came from the same category
and in doing so reveal hidden structure
now classification basically says okay
well we have some B cells and some you
know t- cells and some activated B cells
and some proliferation uh you know uh
cells and then from that we're we're you
know we're going to now classify genes
that are related to these conditions or
conditions that are related to these
genes and so so forth so basically it's
when you have known classes and then
you're
finding features that predict those
classes so the goal is to First extract
features from the the data that best
assign new elements to one or more well
defined
classes sounds good all right
so um I'm I'm showing you this like that
but in fact it's more like this okay
right now we're thinking about oh we
have two Dimensions like measurement in
brain measurement in liver uh and that's
a toy example there's like 22 cells here
and two measurements each in practice
this is what real world data looks like
this is 2.4 million cells across 430
donors every one of which has a 20,000
dimensional Vector okay and going back
to your comment yes you can represent
this into Dimensions using some kind of
nonlinear dimensionality reduction
technique which we're going to talk
about in later lectures everybody with
me here so basically remember that it's
much more complicated but in this
lecture we're going to think about the
simple scenario to introduce the machine
learning components and the inference
little by little okay so basically these
clusters discover one component of the
variation which is the cell type but now
within that cell type the cells here
come from let's say Alzheimer's and the
cells here come from control or the
cells here come from males and the cells
here come from female donors and so so
forth
okay and again single cell analysis a
lot more complex we're going to talk
about that in lecture six you know you
have to deal with batch effects for
example most of the time when you do an
experiment you basically see oh this is
the cells from the first experiment and
this s from the second experiment and
they have nothing to do with each other
so basically what you need to do is find
some anchors that are are sort of the
best you know neighbors for example
between these celles and kind of like
pull them together and then you know
change the dimensionality to match those
Etc so that's the first thing you got to
remove unwanted variation you got to
understand that there's thousands of
genes measured by sell there's like
Dropout events there's a lot of noise
and sparsity because the samples are
tiny you're measuring one cell at a time
there's herity there's all kinds of
scalability issues you got to work with
alignment integration across platforms
and different experim exp Al designs
sometimes the little bubble will catch
two cells instead of one cell and that's
a problem we call these doublets
sometimes you have multiplets and you
have to worry about dimensionality
reduction which can be linear sparse
nonlinear Etc everybody with me here so
all of that will be in lecture six but
for now let's worry about beautiful data
two Dimensions let's clut them okay so
how do you discover these clusters how
do you find you know that these are
micral cells and these are
progenitor cells and so so the way
you're going to do that is by um
assuming that there's some fixed number
of clusters and then partition the
points into those
clusters and how you can
initialize randomly K cluster centers
and then you can repeatedly assign
points to a center and then move the
centers to the center of gravity of
their points and you can stop when
there's no more reassignments let's see
what that looks like so I've sampled
some points without knowing which
distribution generated each of them I
randomly throw three centers yeah this
one you know I may have cheated I put it
very close to those points but this one
is sort of exactly halfway between those
clusters so what's going to happen let's
run the algorithm first I'm going to
assign every data point to the nearest
cluster then I'm going to color the
points based on that nearest cluster and
then I'm going to recalculate the
cluster centers I'm going to move the
Clusters center of gravity of the points
that are assigned to those
clusters notice What's Happening Here
the Green Point the green centroid gets
moved somewhere to that you know average
but because I had the purple Point here
capturing some of those you know we'll
see what happens at the next iteration
so here I've now captured those and
those and now I'm going to move the
Green Point the the the green centroid
closer to the points that are near it
and the points that are near it now the
purple cluster that came down has now
captured all of the points previously
assigned to the green and now the green
gets moved to the center of the
corresponding points everybody with me
so what did I do here I basically just
cooked up a recipe this is like AI I
cooked up a recipe I don't tell if it's
good I don't tell if it's bad I just
simply you know run an algorithm it's
basically just a recipe like the way you
make waffles or Crepes this is just a
recipe now how do we know if it's any
good well we need to evaluate it how do
we know how well it captures the thing
that we were trying to capture we can
have some kind of approximation bound
that basically says here's how good or
how close you get to the op okay but
let's now break it down a little
bit and and then we're going to show
that it's in fact gaussian mixture model
model okay so so in one step we
basically said we're going to assign
points to the nearest Center and in the
other one we updated the center to match
the points okay and guess what this is a
form of learning because I'm actually
getting progressively better at
capturing this unknown structure of the
data it's not supervised learning but it
is a form of learning okay what are we
trying to do what is this algorithm
actually doing what it's actually doing
is that by by reassigning the point to
the nearest center it's actually
minimizing the distance between all of
the points that are assigned and the
centroids to which they're assigned
and when I'm updating the center to the
mean I'm basically you know again re
inferring something
about my representation of the world so
first of all I'm saying which clusters
generate the points and then I'm saying
what is the most likely clusters and if
either of them was known the other one
would be
trivial but because neither of them is
known we're kind of starting with a
random guess of the Clusters
of the centroids and then we're
iterating to improve it and that's going
to be a common technique for many many
algorithms that we see where you
basically start with a randomization and
then you progressively make it
better now you can think of K means as
basically trying to create clusters that
minimize a cost Criterion associated
with the size of the cluster you
basically say that the cost of in
inferring some structure to all of these
points is simply the the sum over all
centroids or clusters of the sum over
all points in every cluster of the total
distance does that make sense so by
making the Clusters compact I can
basically make that cost smaller what's
a great way to make you know this
cluster super compact I have a th points
choose a th
clusters right boom every Point gets a
cluster zero cost function so you know
we basically can't have that one single
measurement as the cost function we also
have to think about generalization you
have to think about the compactness of
the representation and that's a lot of
what we call
regularization regularization basically
means that I'm going to have a penalty
associated with a number of parameters
that I'm using everybody with me here
great but basically for a fixed number
of clusters then this is a fine you know
algorithm that basically minimizes the
of these clusters sounds good and it
turns out that the C algorithm is
basically minimizing this geometric view
of the structure inference of the points
which is we're you know trying to
minimize that total uh sum of distances
and what is that sum of distances
basically the way to do that is simply
the centroid uh of the points is what
minimize okay so you can basically think
of the
um of the algorithm as basically doing
that
now assigning these points
discretely and unambiguously to only one
cluster at a time has a problem which is
that some points can truly be almost
halfway between two centers and
therefore we might want to sort of think
about partial weights and that's going
to be a modification of the Cs algorithm
that's like fuzzy K means and what is
fuzzy K means fuzzy means basically says
we're going to basically assign points
partially to each of the Clusters
instead of saying this point is 100%
blue you say that this point is 98% blue
and maybe 1% purple and you know 0.7%
Green everybody with me here and this
point you know for this point it
probably doesn't make a big difference
but for this point it does it's like 40%
this and 30% that and 20% this or
something like that okay 30 or something
anyway
so the goal here is instead of saying
that there's probability one of being
generated by this cluster and this
cluster only we say that now it's a
probability that really depends on that
distribution of the point so and again
that's where we're getting to the
gaussian mixture model every single one
of the centroids is a
gaussian generating points from this
distribution randomly sampling according
to that Gauss distribution and now when
you see these points you say okay which
gussan is more likely to have generated
at this point okay so now let's think
about the the machine learning
formulation of this nice little recipe
that we saw you basically have the
generative model again I have a model of
the world and I'm sampling points from
that model as we saw earlier so I have a
model of the world that's you know
there's some red points and there's some
Blue
Points so I flip a die and I Choose Or
flip a coin and I choose whether I'm
going to sample from the r distribution
and when I do I basically sample from a
gaan
and therefore the points are going to be
distributed from the center out in an
exponential decay okay and this is the
gaussian distribution it's basically one
over 2 pi and then that that the
exponent and that's the distance and so
so forth so that's the decay of the
gaussian function and the gaussian
function is not just something that you
know humans dreamed up with to make high
school students
suffer it's it's real it's there it's
it's there in the real world so
basically when you create a machine
where every ball will randomly fall on a
stick and then randomly go right or left
with equal probability you end up with
basically a g distribution and it's
spooky how present and omnipresent it is
okay so then you can think about these
centers of mass or the center of gravity
and you can think about the spread of
that distribution and now the question
is if I have gions generating points
with means you know uh here here and
here and here
then what is the most likely G to have
generated a point here well the red one
what about here well the orange one so
the rightmost point comes from the
orange
distribution what about the leftmost
point also the orange
distribution that's a little weird and
that's because it has the longest spread
and therefore the fact that the green
one is slightly to the left of it
matters initially but
eventually stops matter yeah so in the
Ali what's like how do we know one point
on the bottom left of the gra versus one
point the top right of that gra is not
from the same distribution K would
assume they're different distribs right
exactly exactly so basically now we're
getting closer to fuzzy K means and to
expectation maximization so basically
the original K means the geometric
approach only deals with one unit
variance it doesn't understand about
different variances and it doesn't
understand about priors so basically
here in the full model we'll have
different priors for blue versus green
versus red versus orange and different
spreads whereas K means only understands
about the means but not the standard
deviations or the frequeny okay so now
we can go back and revisit this cute
little recipe and basically realize that
it's actually an optimal algorithm for
finding
the interpretation of the world that has
maximum a posterior probability of
generating the points that we observed
is everybody with me here so what we're
going to do is reinterpret these two
steps of the uh K means algorithm in an
expectation
maximization way what is expectation
maximization it's a way to iteratively
refine the latent variable for example
the centers of the point
and
the uh you know rest of the distribution
in an itative fashion instead of
saying
I infer one thing about my data it's an
iterative way to estimate an underlying
posterior distribution that you don't
directly have access to okay so the
Eep assumes that the centers are known
and it estimates the memberships the
mstep assumes that the assignments are
known and recomputes the centroids okay
and iterating between them you basically
have a set of label points oh that's
great super easy I can find the centers
if I have no centers oh super easy I can
assign the points but the iteration
between them is what basically allows me
to get learning machine learning out of
this process okay and then the solution
to the model of the world that Max
maximizes the total probability of
generating this points is no other than
the answer of the cin algorithm
basically what you're trying to do is
solve two problems at once the first is
infer which points were generated by
which clusters and the second one is
what are the Clusters that generated the
points and you can infer both if you
knew any one of them the the other would
be easy but if you don't know either
then you start anywhere and you iterate
okay so then the maximization of this
probability of generating the points
given that gussan again it's a
generative model we have the forward
probability of inferring the X's which
I'm sampling from the gaussian centered
at that
point that total probability the arcmax
of the log
probability is basically the same as
that probability is this expression here
and then this becomes uh you know
irrelevant because it doesn't vary with
X but this here is nothing but the
solution to the centroid problem that we
had
heard okay yeah yeah I'm just a little
bit confused because the
method model also infer variance of the
corre correct only that's exactly right
so basically in the case of the variance
being the same it's identical if the
variance changes now then you know then
we need a a more sophisticated version
of that algorithm okay so basically when
I'm Computing that probability that
probability here is just simply based on
you know this uniformly decaying
function but now if you have a parameter
associated with the spread of that decay
that becomes a standard deviation and
that you scale in that exponent and that
basically becomes a scaling factor that
you're going to need to incorporate in
your um in your algorithm
okay and then again the the same thing
happens with this maximization of either
maximizing the likelihoods of the
cluster means and maximize the
likelihood of a point being generated by
that mean and you can basically think
again side by side about the K means
algorithm the fuzzy K means algorithm
and what is the Eep and the M step and
you know I'll let you you know walk
through that on your own but the initial
King's solution was a uniform prior
where every CL is the same size a unit
distance function instead of
having some variable standard deviation
for your point a symmetric distribution
between the different dimensions of your
data where the every Dimension was
independent the X and the Y were
independent where here we can actually
talk about a covariance matrix of sort
of some you know reshaping of the space
and then with K me we simply picked the
max where we found the one cluster that
was closest and we chose that one and
with fuzzy means we looked at the full
density and with expectation
maximization we can look at the full
density and then estimate the membership
of the points all probabilistically
according to each cluster or we could
even sample from that posterior
distribution using Gib sampling that
we're going to see again in a lecture or
two okay so again if you have an
original data set it was generated by a
big green cluster that was you know
shaped this way and then two little red
and blue clusters the cing solution will
spread them you know exactly that way
will sort of separate the points that
way will partition as should say whereas
the fuli model will be able to sort of
recognize the standard deviation of the
blue is actually larger than the
standard deviation of the green and so
so forth and therefore that point here
even though it's technically closer here
will be a sign there
okay excited good so that's basically uh
expectation maximization and uh
that sort of assumes that we have chosen
a number of clusters and then we're
partitioning into those K clusters okay
but the problem is that selecting K can
be hard you can always make clusters
more compact by increasing K and if K is
the number of data then you know of
course it's you know perfect but
meaningless completely um and with
hierarchical clustering you can you can
kind of side step this so basically
hierarchical clustering is an gomera
clustering that basically says can I
build a nest set of clusters which are
organized as a hierarchy so when I have
a set of points I don't need to choose K
in advance I just find the two closest
points and I merge those I find then you
know then they become a cluster then I
find the next closer there and I merge
the next two closest clusters and I
continue to basically generate an a tree
a hierarchy that basically tells me the
order in which they were clustered okay
and then if I want to uh make a cut I
can just choose how many clusters do I
want and I can just make a cut at that
height and then it gives me the four
clusters everybody here good so this is
upgma that we're going to see again in
philogyny later in the semester which is
unweighted pair group method with
arithmetic
mean and when you do that you assume
that every point is a cluster initially
and when you merge two points together
you merge the corresponding
clusters but the problem is that the
closer to closer
distance is itself matter of debate how
do you calculate the distance between
these cluster in that cluster you could
take the distance of the closest two
points you could take the distance of
the furthest two points and if you
choose this one versus that one this one
will basically allow you to merge
clusters like a snake you know connect
them together whereas this one will sort
of tend to make clusters that are very
compact because it's it wants to make
sure that the two furthest points points
are no further than any other cluster
that I could merge everybody with me
here or you could say let me take all of
the pairwise distances and just average
them and then that will be the cluster
to Cluster distance or I could simply
take the center of gravity and the
center of gravity and you know look at
the distance between the centroids of
those this one is a k squ algorithm this
is an N squ algorithm this is basically
checking all n squ distances this is
only checking all K squ distances where
case the number of clusters at that
point but of course recomputing those
distances basically means that I need to
now that I've merged these clusters I
need to recompute the center of crow
okay so anyway basically the cluster
distance affects both the results and
the run time and again the pointto point
similarity can be either uclean distance
which is what you know most of us
intuitively think of or it could be
Manhattan distance or it could be
Pearson correlation or sper Spellman
correlation and so so forth okay and
then to evaluate the clustering results
you can basically look at some other
independent measurement and say How
likely is it to have sampled I don't
know um K Alzheimer's patients in my
group randomly uh by chance okay so I
want to make a small parenthesis here
because we are in 2024 and people think
of clustering of points with numbers but
you can actually cluster things Beyond
just points Okay so here's of course
clustering of numbers so basically this
is you know 2.4 million cells clustered
according to their expression
patterns um this is now patients
clustered together but you can actually
start clustering text how do you cluster
text you can cluster text by uh and I
don't know if that link will work but
let's find out yooo so um this is
basically clustering of uh responses to
a survey so basically this person says
oh I have a relationship that did not go
as expected as a result it brought me
down personally as a person I'm sorry if
this is very depressing uh so uh as soon
as I said depressing all you guys are
laugh laughing okay um so so basically
um back in 1980 a bunch of old men sat
together in a room and said okay we're
going to Define psychiatric conditions
according to this list and now every one
of us in 2024 has to fit one of those
lists that they decided like 30 40 years
ago okay instead you could say okay let
me just look at the responses of every
person and then based on that I can
infer a hierarchy of you know
psychiatric uh you know conditions
basically all of these are uh parental
health concerns okay this is in Greece
so it's it's a little biased um so uh
you know personal concern summary Etc so
basically relationship breakups so all
of these things it happens to you that's
the thing like you suddenly realize that
it's not just me I'm not the only weird
person who doesn't fit one of those like
1980 categories like all of us are
struggling with some of those things so
um you can basically now you know um
study not just um numbers but also text
you can take the description of every
single human protein just as free text
and then you could cluster those
descriptions together and hopefully that
space will come up and now you can
basically navigate 20,000 genes not
based on their expression but based on
the description of their functions and
if I search here for lipids for example
if I can
spell I can basically find that there
are you know genes associated with
lipids in a bunch of different
categories maybe in cargo receptors or
in biosynthesis and molecular function
Etc you could also do all kinds of fun
things you could like you know select
those points together and say you know
uh what are
uh
some let me make this a little
bigger uh diseases that these genes are
involved in right and then it can
basically you know tell you answers
about that anyway why am i showing you
this because this is so much fun a bunch
of undergrads like mostly freshman and
sophomores in my group built this and it
allows you to now start thinking of text
as uh clusters so this is another fun
space every Lex fredman uh click clip is
now categorized and you can see here uh
unsurprisingly when you zoom into the
center that's where the meaning of life
is and uh you know next to meaning of
life you basically have philosophical
discussions Etc why am i showing you
this because I want you guys to think
broadly Beyond just numbers everybody's
thinking of oh you know I'm going to do
a final project by measuring expression
here and here and there why don't you
just do a co-embedding of you know all
of the expression patterns of you know
uh
a bunch of genes with the lat and
embedding representation of the
corresponding things okay so that's the
sort of small parenthesis and uh all of
this to say that what we just saw is a
much harder version of naive Bas
classification why because with naive
Bas you have classes that you already
know about you have class one and class
two and therefore you can ass
assign probability distributions to the
points from that class so before I was
doing everything from scratch I didn't
know what point belonged where and I
didn't know what the cluster would look
like whereas here you actually know what
points belong where and therefore it's
actually super trivial to infer the
center of mass of that distribution it's
just the average of those points the the
the spread it's just the standard
devation and you can now use that to
start inferring what is the probability
of a given class given the data and how
much more likely is it that something
belongs in class one versus class two
given the data and to and of course as
we mentioned earlier the denominator is
the same so what do you want to know you
want to know the probity of class one
given the data probity pass to given the
data and using Bas
rule this is the backward facing Arrow
this is the forward facing Arrow I Know
How likely it is to generate a
particular expression value given the
class and I know the prior for that
class and the denominator is the same so
I can basically build a basian
classifier between different classes
simply based on the generation
probability times the
prior a lot of people think of vision
statistics oh you just have prior for
everything no the prior just simply
comes from this invert ing the direction
of the arrows part and the prior just
naturally sort of Falls in there and
therefore we can think of a discriminant
function for a classification based on
whenever that probability is greater
than one or whenever the log probability
is greater than two then we classify
according to one class or another class
okay and therefore we can think about
estimating these distributions based on
the number of points that are sitting in
different parts you could assume a
parameterized model which basically
means I have a mean and a standard
deviation or you could assume a
non-parametric model that simply says
I'm just going to you know break up the
distribution in different parts and just
simply measure how much is in each part
if you know that your data is
distributed as a gaan you're doing great
you can just use that if you don't know
then you want to be a little more
unbiased for example it could be a you
know multi Peak distribution or you know
non um bell shaped distribution and so
so forth is everybody here awesome so uh
and then to combine multiple features
that's where you can
assume uh in the naive base scenario you
just assume Independence you assume that
all of these features are independent of
each other and that's the naive Bas
assumption it basically assumes that all
of the features are independent and
therefore that the join probability of
all the features together given a class
is simply each of the features in
isolation and therefore the product of a
bunch of independent classes of course
this is almost never the case however
you could do some kind of principal
component analysis you could basically
separate the all of these different
measurements into a set of separate
principal components and then you can
actually use you know base uh
classification that way okay so again
this was optional so we're not going to
cover it but basically we talked about
uh gene expression analysis we talked
about K means we talked about
hierarchical clustering we talked about
naive based classification and we also
talked about how this does not apply
solely to numbers it can apply to text
and you can really go wild because it is
2024 and you know large language models
are are around and and sort of what I
showed you earlier with the teest
classification this is super trivial
it's basically just looking at the lat
and embedding
representation of a large language model
par of whatever text it is you can
basically you know use that and if you
guys want to use it for your final
projects you know I I would love for all
of you guys to be able to visualize to
sort of zoom in to the different
clusters that you're learning and so on
so forth okay so uh that's where we end
for today and um I will see you guys on
Thursday where we're talking about um
some more fun
stuff so thirdly we're going to talk
about uh he Mark of models dynamic
programming parsing and sequential
data yeah